Rockbridge County Records WLU.Coll.0067
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Rockbridge County Records
Inclusive 1778-1912
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
WLU.Coll.0067
96 Item 32 folders
Scope and Contents
This collection includes Rockbridge County records, including tax lists, ordinary licenses, muster rolls, lists of slaves, court cases, and election polls.
Freedmen; Virginia -- Lexington; Taxation; Registers; Virginia -- Rockbridge County; Slavery; Elections; Court records; Records; Broadsides
- Legal papers, property lists, and misc., 1777-1855 (Box 1, Folder 1-16)
  - Control (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rockbridge County, Va. legal papers, 1777-07-15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Campbell family; Campbell, Patrick
    - Will of Patrick Campbell, 1777-07-15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Will mentions transfer of "negro girl named Agg" to his wife, Ann Campbell who appeared in court and delined legacy of will, resulting in transfer to son, James Campbell.
    - Bond for Ordinary License, Rockbridge County, John Moore, William Alexander, John Paxton, 1778-11-04 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bond for Ordinary License, Rockbridge County, Alexander Stuart, Joseph McCray, 1778-12, December Court 1778 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rockbridge County VA Lists, taxable property 1783, All records hand-written in ink on small scraps of paper (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Andrew Scotts Tax Record, 1 White Tithable; 2 Blacks: man named Samuel and woman named Dinnah (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mary [related to William?] Groves Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Robert Shaw Tax Record, One White tithable; one Negro named Gedion (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Andrew Moore Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - James Patterson tax record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - David Moore tax record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Robert McCormick tax record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - George Campbell Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Samuel WC [illegible] tax record, one Negro woman named Luise [spelling?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - John Pamler [illegible - spelling?] tax record, Negro woman named Bess (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - William Moore Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - John Parks Tax Record, one Negro man named Cook (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - David Moore tax record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - James Patton tax record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - John A. of William Moore Township [?] Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - James Paxton Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - John Pur.. [illegible] Tax Records (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - William McClung Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Alexandre Moore Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hugh Beard Tax Record, One Slave named Joe (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Anne Caruthers Tax Record, "too nigers" (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Thomas Steele Tax Records (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - James McClung Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - James Parker Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - James Statton [?] Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - John Kerr Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jonathan Williamson Tax Record, Name does not appear in Fothergill's Virginia Taxpayers 1782-1787 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - David Moore Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Joseph Seat Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Abraham Wein Tax Record, one slave name Sall (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Alexander Green Tax Record, One Negro Boy named Ritchman 16 years of age (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Joseph [illegible] Tax Record, one slave named Emery under 16 years of age (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - James McGowry Tax Record, i Negro Girl named Mille (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Samuel Eakin Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Archibald Henderson Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - William Alexander Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jeane Weir Tax Record, 1 Negro under 16 named Dick (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Nathaniel Wilson Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - David Williamson Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Samuel Wilson Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - David Chambers (?) Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - John Craig Tax Record, "1 white tithable; 1 white under 21" (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - James Bell Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Samuel Eakin Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rockbridge County, VA Lists of Taxable Property 1786 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Jonathan Starrit Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - James Tedford Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Multiple Tax Records on single sheet: Adam Reid, William Reid, Daniel Reid, James Anderson, Thomas Black, David Tedford, Peter Lowery, John Tedford, William Ferguson, David Hinkaston, Abraham Draper, John McCamey, Robert McCamey, William Lusby, George Cavin (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Isaac Anderson (& William Anderson) Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - John Tedford Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Andrew Campbell Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - John McCrosky Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - William McCutchens Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - John McCampbell Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - James McKemy Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Alex Stewart Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Robert Everitt Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Robert Stuart Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Isaac Jackson Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - James McCampbell Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - James Weir Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - William Campbell Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Samuel Kilpatrick Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - James Dickson Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - William Walker Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - James Wilson Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Solomon Campbell Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - William McHenry Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Elizabeth McCray Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - William McHenry Tax Record (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Invoice dated 1786 (without specific month or day) from Thomas Tate for wheel (appears to be unrelated to taxes); unsigned; references "balance on account" (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rockbridge County, VA 1784-1800 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Rockbridge County Court May 6, 1784 William Alexander and William Moore bond for Ordinary license (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - List of revenue taxes collected by Rockbridge County Deputy Sheriff from January to May 1787 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Agreement between Michael Goore & James Seers concerning "a Negro man named Adam" and the care of Seers during his lifetime dated February 3, 1789 in Rockbrdge County Court (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Conveyance of land by Hugh McDowell and his wife Sarah to William Hayes in Rockbridge County Court on October 5, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Josias Anderson and John Galbraith bond for Ordinary license Rockbridge County Court February 7, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Certificate of ownership John Templeton 3-year-old bay mare colt appraised at 4 pounds 5 shillings January 2, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bond for Ordinary license Rockbridge County Josias Anderson and John Galbraith September 1, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bond for Ordinary license Rockbridge County John Mackey and John McKee February 2, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Inventory of estate of William Walos (deceased) February 29, 1792 Rockbridge County, VA (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Settlement of a debt between the estate of John Hays and James Herran Rockbridge County Court June 28, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - List of conveyances of land recorded in the office of the Rockbridge County Court May 1, 1797 to May 1, 1798 within the Southwest District (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rockbridge County, VA 1784-1800 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - List of Land Grants issued in Rockbridge County from November 1, 1814 to October 1, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Rockbridge County election poll 1813 (Breckenridge vs. McFerrin) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Typed letter from Virginia State Library dated May 20. 1913 attaching Pay Roll of Captain James Paxton's Company of the Second Corps D'Elite "in the service of the United States, commanded by Col. Moses Green, at Camp Charles City Courthouse, from the 31st August to the 29th December 1814" [includes David Paxton, Elisha Paxton, and Alexander Paxton] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rockbridge County, VA Property List 1815 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Persons owning land in Rockbridge County in 1815 (including listings of their property--horses, cattle, slaves, etc. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rockbridge County, VA Case of McClure vs. Crawford 1815 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Case of McClure vs. Crawford Staunton District Court 1815 (father, Malcolm, died leaving estate partially to children; mother remarried; children sued to get their share) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rockbridge County, VA Two Legal Cases covering material between 1812 and 1841 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Case of Margaret Irvine and her estranged husband John McCue before Judge Lucas Thompson, Superior Court of Chancery for Rockbridge County 1838 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Case of Sarah Patton before Judge Lucas Thompson, Superior Court of Chancery for Rockbridge County, regarding 1812 and 1822 wills of late husband James Patton and children Matthew and William who predeceased her estate then managed by son-inlaw George Ireland of Rockbridge County and grandson William P. McDowell of Tennessee. Question of ownership of slaves. Latest date February 12, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rockbridge County, VA Tax List and Bonds of Rockbridge County Court 1830-1832 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Handwritten list covering Rockbridge County taxes, September 1830 to August 1831 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - $50,000 surety bond for paving the streets and providing water for the town of Lexington for two years from July 21, 1832 William Fisher and Andrew H. Jordan (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Separate $20,000 surety bond for paving the streets and providing water for the town of Lexington for two years from July 21, 1832 William Fisher and Andrew H. Jordan (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rockbridge County, VA Military Records 1834-1840 - Rockbridge Union Volunteers (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Court summons to John Keller regarding debt owed to Francis Smith January 10, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letter June 2, 1834 to Rockbridge Union Volunteers regarding accommodations from Kenton Hanlen in Staunton (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Members of Rockbridge Union Volunteers absent from regimental muster for May 1837 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Invitation to Capt. G.A. Baker inviting Lexington Volunteers to participate in celebration on February 17, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Members of Rockbridge Union Volunteers absent from June muster 1839 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Members of Rockbridge Union Volunteers Company absent from parade July 4, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Members of Rockbridge Union Volunteers Company absent from muster in November 1836 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Members of Rockbridge Union Volunteers Company present at muster in April 1837 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Treasurer's Report Rockbridge Union Volunteers Company August 2, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Requisition to Capt. David Moore (Commandant of the Public Guard) of 75 muskets from the Lexington Arsenal for the Rockbridge Union Volunteers Company January 1, 1834 - A.T. Barclay Capt. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Treasurer's Report Rockbridge Union Volunteers Company March 1837 (Box 1, Volume 11)
    - Roll of members of Rockbridge Union Volunteers Company January 6, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Members of Rockbridge Union Volunteers Company absent from muster on August 4, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Members of Rockbridge Union Volunteers Company absent from muster in September 1838 (?) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Treasurer's Report Rockbridge Union Volunteers Company February 17, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Rockbridge Union Volunteers - Address July 4, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Address on the 4th of July 1838 - Rockbridge Union Volunteers - by Robert Taylor (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Various Court Documents - 1841-1845 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Request to exempt slave named Jacob from taxation - April 5, 1841 Andrew Alexander (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Request to exempt slaves from taxation - May 2, 1841 Elisha Grigsby (Ralph--between 85-90, Milla--67 and afflicted with rheumatism, Prince--65 "for the last 30 years afflicted with a sore leg") (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "List of Free Negroes" found within the SW revenue district of Rockbridge August 5, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 12 pages of written receipts for paid Rockbridge County Court debts 1844 (numbered 2 to 13, but missing page 1) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 3 miscellaneous receipts for payments January 1, 1844; March 11, 1844; August 7, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Public Hiring of Free Negroes Printed Bill (Poster) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Public Hiring of Free Negroes" February 6, 1855 "BY order of the County Court of Rockbridge County, made on the 6th day of February, 1854, I shall, on the first day of March Court next, offer for hire the following FREE NEGROES, for the purpose of paying their taxes.... Gentlemen wishing to hire hands will not have a chance of hiring cheaper than at the March Court. I am bound under the law not to hire them for less than ten cents per day. They are hired running at large. I am not responsible for their delivery. JNO. J. M. GILBERT, D.S. for John A. M. Lush. S.R.C.", Broadside (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Rockbridge County, VA original U.S. Congressional Election Polls, May 24, 1855 (John Letcher vs. William Seymour) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at the Courthouse of Rockbridge County in District No. 1 on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at Dryden's School House, Broad Creek in District No. 2 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at Paxton's School House in District No. 2 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at Natural Bridge in District No. 3 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at Hamilton School House in District No. 4 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at Collierstown in District No. 4 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at Trevey in District No. 5 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at Lowman's Mill in District No. 5 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at Brownburg in District No. 6 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at Goshen in District No. 6 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at Fairfield in District No. 7 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poll held at Wilson's Shop in District No. 7 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for the election of a member to represent the District of which Rockbridge is a part in the Congress of the United States (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Rockbridge, VA original Virginia Senate Election Polls May 24, 1855 (James H. Paxton vs. A.G. McGriffin) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at the Courthouse of Rockbridge County in District No. 1 on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at Paxton's School House in District No. 2 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at Dryden's School House, Broad Creek in District No. 2 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at Natural Bridge in District No. 3 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at Hamilton's School House in District No. 4 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at Collierstown in District No. 4 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted). (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at Lowman's Mill in District No. 5 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at Trevey in District No. 5 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at Brownsburg in District No. 6 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at Goshen in District No. 6 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at Fairfield in District No. 7 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poll held at Wilson's Shop in District No. 7 of Rockbridge County on Thursday the 24th day of May A.D. 1855 for purpose of electing a Senator to represent the District composed of the Counties of Rockbridge, Bath, & Highland in the next Senate of Virginia (contains the name of every voter and how they voted (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Legal papers, property lists, and misc., 1777-1855 (Box 2, Folder 17-32)
  - Lexington, VA - Military Records - Militia Roll 1858-1859 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - booklet containing alphabetized Rockbridge militia attendance records for October 1858, April 1859, and May1859 -- includes officers and privates (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Call for Slaves by the Commonwealth for its public defense November 27, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Official notice addressed to the Clerk of the County Court of Rockbridge from George Munford, Secretary of the Commonwealth, Executive Department, Richmond, November 27, 1862 including a copy of "An Act to Further Provide for the Public Defense passed October 3, 1862' (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Taxation Records (Southwestern Section) 1862 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Alphabetical booklet listing taxes by name and category (real estate, slaves, bank stock, RR and otbher Corporation Stock, Money at Interest, Cash on Hand or on Deposit, Cattles, Horses, & Mules, Gold or Silver Watches, Silver Plate on Jewelry, Pianos, Pleasure Carriages, Bank or Corporate Stock not duly returned, Misc. ….) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Slaves Exempt from Draft 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - William Watterson January 13, 1863 "incapacity for labor of my negro man Nick—he not able to do any outdoor work for two months past" (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Notice of Justice of the Peace January 14, 1863 Robert C. McClean has disabled boy Trotter; slave has rheumatism January 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Two of Mr. Adams negro men are critically unfit for any service whatever January 14, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Joseph McClung's "black man Charles" has for part two months been confined with inflammatory rheumatism Jan 13, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Collierstown January 8, 1863 slave Jacob unfit for service in the military department because of disease of the hand (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - John McKeny's boy Henry had a severe attack of pneumonia followed by scarlet fever Jan 14, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - James Wilson appeared before Justice of the Peace and made an oath that his boy Sam had a severe spell of sickness January 12, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - William Wittmore stated on Jan 13, 1863 that his "Negro man Nick" had not been able to do any work for two months (a doctor's certificate from Brownsburg is attached) (Box 2, Folder 20)